<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on April 27, 2021</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00135629</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DHRG-UpDosing</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00135629</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Factors Predicting Efficacy of Allergen Injection Immunotherapy for Grass Pollen Hayfever</brief_title>
  <official_title>Factors Predicting Efficacy of Allergen Injection Immunotherapy for Grass Pollen Hayfever: A Pilot Study. (Up-dosing Study)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Imperial College London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>ALK-Abelló A/S</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Imperial College London</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine at which point in the dosing regime grass pollen&#xD;
      immunotherapy causes a significant reduction in the late skin response to allergen challenge.&#xD;
      A once weekly cluster regimen of 2 injections per visit was employed during the up-dosing&#xD;
      phase, followed by monthly maintenance injections of 100,000 SQ units. Symptom scores and&#xD;
      need of rescue medication were recorded by patients during the study period. The size of&#xD;
      early and late cutaneous response to allergen challenge was recorded and measured by a&#xD;
      physician.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This was a single centre, randomised, double-blind placebo controlled trial of grass pollen&#xD;
      injection immunotherapy (Alutard SQ, ALK Abello, Denmark) in adults with severe summer&#xD;
      hayfever unresponsive to antihistamines and topical steroids. The main aim was to determine&#xD;
      at which point in the dosing regime grass pollen immunotherapy causes a significant reduction&#xD;
      in the late skin response to allergen challenge. A once weekly cluster regimen of 2&#xD;
      injections per visit was employed during the up-dosing phase, followed by monthly maintenance&#xD;
      injections of 100,000 SQ units. Twelve patients received active treatment (mean age 31, 7&#xD;
      male) whilst 6 were given placebo (mean age 37, 2 male). The 24 hour skin response (size of&#xD;
      swelling, (mm)) to intradermal allergen challenge (0.1, 1, 10 BU) was determined on alternate&#xD;
      weeks during the 8 week up-dosing phase and then monthly up to 6 months and 3 monthly up to&#xD;
      11-13 months following initiation of treatment.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Results:&#xD;
&#xD;
      At the end of the up-dosing phase (approximately 8 weeks) there was a significant reduction&#xD;
      in the size of the late phase response which was evident with all three intradermal doses&#xD;
      (p=0.02 for 0.1 &amp; 1 BU and p=0.04 for 10 BU). This reduction was sustained throughout the&#xD;
      maintenance phase (p=0.04 for 0.1 BU and 0.01 for 1&amp; 10BU).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Conclusion:&#xD;
&#xD;
      The up-dosing phase of grass pollen immunotherapy alone is sufficient to dampen the late skin&#xD;
      response to allergen challenge. Whether or not this may be predictive of the clinical&#xD;
      response to immunotherapy remains to be determined.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>October 2002</start_date>
  <completion_date>February 2004</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptom and medication score recorded by subjects</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rhinoconjunctivitis Quality of Life Questionnaire</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intradermal allergen challenge</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment>18</enrollment>
  <condition>Rhinitis, Allergic, Seasonal</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sublingual Alutard SQ grass pollen tablets (Phleum pratense)</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Venepuncture: 100ml blood sample taken on 12 separate visits</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Male and female 18-65 years of age&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Written informed consent obtained before entering the trial&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  A clinical history of grass pollen induced allergic rhinoconjunctivitis of two years&#xD;
             or more requiring treatment during the grass pollen season&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  A clinical history of severe rhinoconjunctivitis symptoms (interfering with usual&#xD;
             daily activities or sleep), which remain troublesome despite treatment with&#xD;
             anti-allergic drugs during the grass pollen season&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Positive Skin Prick Test (SPT) response (wheal diameter ≥ 3 mm) to Phleum pratense&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Positive specific IgE against Phleum pratense (≥ IgE Class 2)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Physical examination with no clinically relevant findings&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  If pre-menopausal female of childbearing potential, the subject must test negative on&#xD;
             standard urine pregnancy test and must be willing to practice appropriate&#xD;
             contraceptive methods for the duration of the trial&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Willingness to comply with this protocol&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  FEV1 &lt; 70% of predicted value&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  A clinical history of symptomatic seasonal allergic rhinitis and/or asthma due to tree&#xD;
             pollen or weed pollen adjacent to the start of - and potentially overlapping - the&#xD;
             grass pollen season&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  A clinical history of significant symptomatic perennial allergic rhinitis and/or&#xD;
             asthma caused by an allergen to which the subject is regularly exposed&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  A clinical history of significant recurrent acute sinusitis (defined as 2 episodes per&#xD;
             year for the last two years all of which required antibiotic treatment) or chronic&#xD;
             sinusitis&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  At randomisation, current symptoms of, or treatment for, upper respiratory tract&#xD;
             infection, acute sinusitis, acute otitis media or other relevant infectious process&#xD;
             (serous otitis media is not an exclusion criterion)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  History of emergency visit or admission for asthma in the previous 12 months&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Use of an investigational drug within 30 days prior to screening&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Previous treatment by immunotherapy with grass pollen allergen or any other allergen&#xD;
             within the previous 5 years&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  History of anaphylaxis, including anaphylactic food allergy, bee venom anaphylaxis,&#xD;
             exercise anaphylaxis or drug induced anaphylaxis&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  History of angioedema&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any of the following underlying conditions known or suspected to be present:&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Cystic fibrosis&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Malignancy&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Insulin-dependent diabetes&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Malabsorption or malnutrition&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Renal or hepatic insufficiency&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Chronic infection&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Drug dependency or alcoholism&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Ischemic heart disease or angina requiring current daily medication or with any&#xD;
                  evidence of disease making implementation of the protocol or interpretation of&#xD;
                  the protocol results difficult or jeopardising the safety of the subject (e.g.&#xD;
                  clinically significant cardiovascular, serious immunopathologic, immunodeficiency&#xD;
                  whether acquired or not, hepatic, neurologic, psychiatric, endocrine, or other&#xD;
                  major systemic disease)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Immunosuppressive treatment&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  History of hypersensitivity to the excipients of the trial medications&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  History of allergy, hypersensitivity or intolerance to trial medications or rescue&#xD;
             medications&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  A mental condition rendering the subject unable to understand the nature, scope and&#xD;
             possible consequences of the trial, and/or evidence of an uncooperative attitude&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Unlikely to be able to complete the trial, for any reason, or likely to travel for&#xD;
             extended periods of time during the grass pollen season&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephen R Durham, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Royal Brompton Hospital, Imperial College, National Heart &amp; Lung Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Brompton Hospital, NHLI Imperial College</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>SW3 6LY</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2010</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 25, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 25, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 26, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 22, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 22, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 23, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Hayfever</keyword>
  <keyword>Sublingual Immunotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Grass pollen immunotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Late cutaneous response</keyword>
  <keyword>Intradermal allergen challenge</keyword>
  <keyword>Seasonal Allergic Rhinoconjunctivitis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rhinitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rhinitis, Allergic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rhinitis, Allergic, Seasonal</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>
